Guide to the Edward H. and Lotta C. Hume Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- EDWARD H. HUME: WRITINGS, 1907-1956, undated; Series IV; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Articles and Professional Papers
    - "Medicine in China, Old and New" (Box 10, Folder 203)
    - "Militarists Jockeying for Supremacy in China" (Box 10, Folder 204)
    - "Missions in China - Today and Tomorrow" (Box 10, Folder 204)
    - "Modern Hospital in the American Community" (Box 10, Folder 205)
    - "Modern Medical Research Takes Root in China" (Box 10, Folder 205)
    - "Modern Responsibility for Health" (Box 10, Folder 206)
    - "New Medicine for Ancient Fears" (Box 10, Folder 207)
    - "New Monuments for Old" (Box 10, Folder 208)
    - "New Pathogenic Bacillus Isolated from a Case Diagnosed As Typhoid Fever" (Box 10, Folder 209)
    - "New President of China" (Box 10, Folder 209)
    - "Note on an Early Third Century Record of Anaesthesia" (Box 10, Folder 210)
    - "Note on Media for Distinguishing B. coli, B. typhosus…" (Box 10, Folder 211)
    - "Note on Narcotics in Ancient Greece and in Ancient China" (Box 10, Folder 211)
    - "Notes on Recent Experiments…" (Box 10, Folder 212)
    - "Old Discouragements and New Hopes in China" (Box 11, Folder 213)
    - "On This Green Hill" (Box 11, Folder 213)
    - "Our Debt to Asia" (Box 11, Folder 213)
    - "Peter Parker and the Introduction of Anesthesia into China" (Box 11, Folder 214)
    - "Pioneering Over the New Changsha-Wuchang Railway" (Box 11, Folder 214)
    - "Present Trends in Christian Hospital Service in China" (Box 11, Folder 214)
    - "Protestant Missions Look Ahead in China" (Box 11, Folder 214)
    - "'Public Welfare Movements in Hunan" (Box 11, Folder 214)
    - "Purchasing Peace with China" (Box 11, Folder 214)
    - "Qui Transtulit Sustinet" (Box 11, Folder 214)
    - "Recent Developments in China's Struggle Towards National Unity" (Box 11, Folder 215)
    - "Reconstruction Even During a Period of Confusion in China" (Box 11, Folder 215)
    - "Relationships in Medicine between Asia and the Modern World" (Box 11, Folder 216)
    - "Relationships in Medicine between China and the Western World" (Box 11, Folder 217)
    - "Religion and Healing" (Box 11, Folder 217)
    - "Signs of National Consciousness in China" (Box 11, Folder 218)
    - "Sino-Japanese Situation" (Box 11, Folder 218)
    - "Situation in Hunan" (Box 11, Folder 218)
    - "Some Foundations of Chinese Medicine" (Box 11, Folder 219)
    - "Some Needed Developments in Graduate Medical Education" (Box 11, Folder 219)
    - "Some Needed Emphasis in Graduate Medical Education" (Box 11, Folder 219)
    - "South China Patriot" (Box 11, Folder 220)
    - "The Square Kettle" (Box 11, Folder 220)
    - "Structure for the Housing of Ideas" (Box 11, Folder 221)
    - "Struggle of Minds and the Struggle of Arms in China" (Box 11, Folder 221)
    - "Surgery In China" (Box 11, Folder 221)
    - "Tariff Conference and Civil War Alternate in Holding Public Attention" (Box 11, Folder 222)
    - "Three Health Revolutions" (Box 11, Folder 223)
    - "Till It Was All Leavened" (Box 11, Folder 223)
    - "Treatment of Wounds in China" (Box 11, Folder 224)
    - "True Builders of a New China" (Box 11, Folder 224)
    - "True Leaders Found amid China's Turmoil" (Box 11, Folder 225)
    - "United States and China" (Box 11, Folder 225)
    - "Western World's Interest in the Manchurian Situation" (Box 11, Folder 226)
    - "What American Education Has Done for China" (Box 11, Folder 227)
    - "What Holds China Together" (Box 11, Folder 228)
    - "What Social Service Means to the Private Hospitals" (Box 11, Folder 228)
    - "Where Goes the Far East?" (Box 11, Folder 228)
    - "White Sun in a Blue Sky above a Field of Blood" (Box 11, Folder 228)
    - "Why the Problem of China Should Grip Every American" (Box 11, Folder 228)
    - "Will Federal Government Succeed in China?" (Box 11, Folder 228)
    - "Without Shedding of Blood…!" (Box 11, Folder 228)
    - "Worship is Essential to Life in India, China, and Arabia" (Box 11, Folder 228)
    - "'Wouldest Thou Be Made Whole?'" (Box 11, Folder 228)
    - "Yale Breaking Through China's Conservatism" (Box 11, Folder 229)
    - "Young China" (Box 11, Folder 229)
    - "The Story of Yung Wing" (Box 11, Folder 230)
  - Poems
    - Sonnets (Box 11, Folder 231-233)
  - Book Reviews
    - The Chinese Mind by Gung-Hsing Wang, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 234)
    - A History of Medicine by Douglas Gutherie, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 234)
    - The Medical Sciences in the German Universities by Theodore Billroth, 1925 (Box 11, Folder 234)
    - Preparing for Post-War Work Abroad by Hazel A. Goff, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 234)
  - Memorials to Friends and Colleagues
    - "Harvey Cushing as I Remember Him" (Box 11, Folder 235)
    - "Henry Winters Luce" (Box 11, Folder 235)
    - "My Friend Ned Harkness" (Box 11, Folder 235)
    - "Nina Diadamia Gage" (Box 11, Folder 235)
    - "Recollections of Dr. William Henry Welch, a Great Teacher" (Box 11, Folder 235)
    - "Tan Yen Kai" (Box 11, Folder 235)
    - "The Vision of a Yale Man, Warren B. Seabury" (Box 11, Folder 235)
  - Research Notes
    - Miscellaneous research notes (Box 11, Folder 236-238)
- LOTTA C. HUME: CORRESPONDENCE, 1910-1972, undated; Series V; .5 linear feet (2 boxes)
  The correspondence of Lotta C. Hume is arranged in two sections: General Correspondence and Correspondence with Charlotte Hume and Norman Freeman. Within each section letters are arranged chronologically.
  - General Correspondence
    - 1910, 1933 - 1972 (Box 12, Folder 239-242)
    - Re: Drama at the Doctor's Gate, 1961 - 1964 (Box 12, Folder 243)
    - Re: Favorite Children's Stories from China and Tibet, 1968 - 1971 (Box 12, Folder 244)
  - Correspondence with Charlotte Hume and Norman Freeman
    - 1930 (Box 12, Folder 245)
    - 1931 (Box 12, Folder 246)
    - 1932 (Box 12, Folder 247)
    - 1933 (Box 12, Folder 248-249)
    - 1934 (Box 12, Folder 250-251)
    - 1935 (Box 12, Folder 252)
    - 1936 (Box 12, Folder 253)
    - 1937 (Box 12, Folder 254)
    - 1938-1940 (Box 12, Folder 255)
    - 1944-1945 (Box 12, Folder 256)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 12, Folder 257)
    - 1948-1950 (Box 13, Folder 258)
    - 1951-1954 (Box 13, Folder 259)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 13, Folder 260)
    - 1958-1972 (Box 13, Folder 261)
    - undated (Box 13, Folder 262)
- LOTTA C. HUME: WRITINGS, 1933-1962, undated; Series VI; .75 linear feet (1 1/2 boxes)
  The materials in Series VI are arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Drama at the Doctor's Gate, pages 1-54, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 263)
  - Drama at the Doctor's Gate, pages 55-132, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 264)
  - Drama at the Doctor's Gate, pages 133-175, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 265)
  - Favorite Children's Stories from China and Tibet, 1962 (Box 13, Folder 266)
  - "The Human Touch at Yali", undated (Box 13, Folder 267)
  - "Lockhart Scott Carswell, a Portrait By His Daughter", 1933 (Box 13, Folder 268)
  - "Marriage Customs in Changsha", undated (Box 13, Folder 269)
  - "Reflections on a 95th Birthday", 1972 (Box 13, Folder 270)
  - "Round the World to Balance a Family Budget", undated (Box 13, Folder 271)
  - "We Dine with Dr. Albert Schweitzer", undated (Box 13, Folder 272)
  - Folktales (Box 13, Folder 273)
  - Folktales (Box 14, Folder 274-277)
  - Research notes and ideas for stories (Box 14, Folder 278-283)
- LOTTA C. HUME: MISCELLANY, 1957-1976; Series VII; 0.25; (1 box)
  The materials in LOTTA C. HUME: MISCELLANY are grouped together according to form.
  - Biographical data and obituary notices, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 284)
  - Financial records
    - 1957-1968 (Box 14, Folder 285)
    - 1970-1972 (Box 14, Folder 286)
    - 1973-1975 (Box 14, Folder 287)
- CORRESPONDENCE, Series VIII
  - Edward H. Hume to Lotta C. Hume
    - 1919 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 1931-1935 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - 1936 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - 1937 (Box 15, Folder 4-5)
    - 1938-1939 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - 1940 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - 1941 (Box 15, Folder 8-9)
    - 1942 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - 1943-1945 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - 1946 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - 1947 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - 1949-1951 (Box 15, Folder 14)
- Additional Material, 1897, 1908-1982, undated; Accession 1991-M-019; 0.25; (1 box)
  Addition inventory by Carol King, 1990 Aug
  Received from: Charlotte Freeman, 1990 Aug 17
  - Correspondence to Charlotte Hume Freeman, 1925 January 22, 1982 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia, printed matter, 1943, 1951, 1953, 1957, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs
    - Edward H. Hume, 1897, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Edward H. Hume and Lotta C. Hume, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Lotta C. Hume, 1929, 1964, 1966, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Yali faculty, 1908-1909 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - China, 1921, 1925, 1935-1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - India, [1937?] (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Additional Material, 1933-1989; Accession 1995-M-124
  - Edward H. Hume Memorial Lectureship [correspondence], 1983, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Manuscripts and Press Articles by Edward Hicks Hume, M.D., LL.D., 1876-1957" [index presented to the Missionary Research Library, New York, by Mrs. Edward Hicks Hume], 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Role of Edward H. Hume in the Advancement of Modern Medical Practice in Hunan, China (1905-1916)," senior essay by Jennifer Lynne Trainor, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs
    - Edward Sackett Hume and Charlotte Chandler Hume [parents of Edward Hicks Hume], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Hsiang River scenes, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lotta Carswell Hume Memorial Scholarship [correspondence, printed material], 1976-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Memorial services for Lotta Carswell Hume [eulogies], 1976 March 6-7 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Return to China Sixty Years Later," Hopkins, by Charlotte Hume Freeman, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Great Wall of China [printed materials, newsclippings], 1933, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)